that there is this huge variety of different sizes, shapes and even colors. The feather is one of the most astonishing pieces of technology invented by the natural world, and for centuries, this feather has helped birds to keep dry, to keep warm and even power flight. Only one section of the tree of life can actually make a feather. Among all the world's animals, birds are the only ones who can make something like what I'm holding today. I personally have given them a nickname, and I like to call them the feathermakers. It is the major difference between birds and any other animals we have on earth, and if you can't make a feather, you cannot call yourself a bird. (Laughter) For us humans, who are earthbound, birds represent freedom. This feather has enabled birds to conquer gravity and take to the air in an extraordinary way. Don't you sometimes wish you could fly like a bird? Birds are my passion, and I want to change the way each one of you thinks about them. The easiest reason I love them so much is because they are beautiful. There are 10,000 species in the world, and each one of them is uniquely beautiful. Birds are amazing, and this talk is dedicated to all the birds of the world. (Laughter) (Applause) Indeed, these birds have been part of our lives and cultures all over the world for centuries, and every society has a story about birds. You probably have heard childhood stories of different birds and how they relate with man. I personally recently learned that our human ancestors would follow flocks of vultures and then they would help them to identify where carcasses have been dropped by large carnivores, and these humans will scavenge and eat part of that meat. Birds have been used as brands and labels all over the world. You know the bald eagle? It was chosen as the national emblem for the US because of its majestic strength, beautiful looks and even a long lifespan. And just like us humans who have managed to live in virtually all habitats of this earth, birds have also conquered the world. From birds such as these beautiful penguins that live in the cold ice caps to even others like the larks, who live in the hottest deserts you can imagine. Indeed, these species have conquered this world. Birds also build houses like us.
hay una gran cantidad de tamaños, formas y colores. La pluma es una de las tecnologías más asombrosas creada por el mundo natural, y por siglos, esta pluma ha ayudado a las aves a estar secas, mantenerse calientes y poder volar. Solo una sección del árbol de la vida puede crear una pluma. De todos los animales del mundo, solo los pájaros pueden crear algo como lo que tengo aquí. Personalmente les he dado un apodo, y me gusta decirles fabricantes de plumas. Es la mayor diferencia entre las aves y cualquier otro animal en la tierra, y si no puedes hacer una pluma, no puedes decir que eres un ave. (Risas) Para los humanos, que no podemos volar los pájaros representan libertad. Esta pluma ha hecho que las aves conquisten la gravedad y vuelen de una manera extraordinaria. ¿No quisieran poder volar como un pájaro? Las aves son mi pasión. Y quiero cambiar su forma de pensar en cuanto a ellas. La razón mas obvia por la que las amo es porque son hermosas. Hay 10 000 especies en el mundo, y cada una de ellas es hermosa a su manera. Las aves son asombrosas, y esta charla está dedicada a todas las aves del mundo. (Risas) (Aplausos) De hecho, estas aves han sido parte de nuestras vidas y culturas por siglos en todo el mundo, y cada sociedad tiene su historia con las aves. Seguramente han escuchado historias infantiles de diferentes aves y cómo se relacionan con el humano. Hace poco aprendí que nuestros ancestros seguían bandadas de buitres y ellos les ayudaban a ver dónde los carnívoros arrojaban los cadáveres, y estos humanos buscaban y comían parte de esa carne. Las aves se han usado como marcas y etiquetas en todo el mundo. ¿Conocen al águila calva? Fue elegida como el emblema nacional de EE. UU. por su fuerza majestuosa, su hermosa apariencia y su alta expectativa de vida. Y al igual que los humanos que han logrado vivir en todos los hábitats de esta tierra, las aves también han conquistado el mundo. Desde estos hermosos pingüinos que viven en estos casquetes de hielo hasta aves como las alondras, que viven en los desiertos más tórridos que existen. Sin duda, estas especies han conquistado este mundo. Las aves también construyen casas como nosotros.
The real pros in housebuilding are a group of birds we call the weaverbirds, and this name they were given because of the way in which they weave their nests. An interesting one: birds also love and date just like us humans. In fact, you'll be surprised to know that males dress to impress the women, and I'll show you how. So here we have a long-tailed widowbird, and this is how they would normally look. But when it comes to the breeding season, everything changes, and this is how he looks. (Audience murmurs) Yeah? Birds also, multiple species of them,
Los verdaderos profesionales en esto son un grupo de aves llamados aves tejedoras, y se les dio este nombre por la manera en que tejen sus nidos. Esto es interesante: a las aves también les gusta tener citas como los humanos. Les impresionará saber que los machos se visten para impresionar a las hembras. Y les mostraré cómo. Aquí tenemos un obispo colilargo. y así es como ellos se ven normalmente. Pero cuando llega la época de la reproducción, todo cambia, y así es como se ve. (Murmullos de la audiencia) ¿Si? A muchas especies de aves
do love to touch and cuddle just like humans. And I know you're wondering about this one. Yes, they kiss too, sometimes very deeply. (Applause) Some have even learned to cheat on their spouses. (Laughter) For example, the African jacana: the females will mate with multiple males and then she takes off to find other males to mate with and she leaves the male behind to take care of the chicks. (Laughter) (Applause) And birds help us so much, and they play very crucial roles in our ecosystems each day. Vultures clean up our environment by literally digesting disease-causing pathogens, and they finish carcasses that would otherwise cost us lots of money to clear from the environment. A sizable flock of vultures is capable of bringing down a carcass the size of a zebra straight to the bone within just about 30 minutes. Owls help to rid the environments of rodents and this helps us a lot because it saves us money -- we don't lose our crops -- and secondly, we don't have to buy harmful chemicals to handle these rodents. The beautiful sunbirds we see in our environments are part of nature's pollination crew, and they help our plants to form fruits. Together with other pollinators like insects, they have actually helped us to get most of the food crops that we depend on for many years. Unfortunately, the story of birds is by far not perfect. They are faced by numerous challenges every day wherever they live. Top on the threats facing birds is habitat loss and reduced food availability. Birds are also hunted, especially migratory species and ducks that congregate in water bodies. Poisoning is happening to flocks that like to stick together, especially in places like rice schemes. Moreover, power lines are electrocuting birds and wind farms are slicing birds when they fly through the blades. Recently, we've heard the talk of climate change making a lot of headlines, and it's also affecting birds, because birds are being forced to migrate to better breeding and feeding grounds because unfortunately where they used to live is no longer habitable. My own perspective towards birds was changed when I was a small boy in high school, and there was this boy who struck, injuring the wing and the leg of a bird we called the augur buzzard. I was standing there, just a mere 14-year-old, and I imagined a human being in a similar situation, because this bird could not help itself. So even if I was hardly any biologist by then, I gathered with three of my friends and we decided to house the bird until it had regained strength and then let it free. Interestingly, it accepted to feed on beef from our school kitchen, and we hunted termites around the compound for its dinner every day. After a few days, it had regained strength and we released it. We were so happy to see it flap its wings and fly off gracefully. And that experience changed the way we looked at birds. We went on to actually make a magazine, and we called it the Hawk Magazine, and this was in honor of this bird
también les gusta tocarse y abrazarse, tal como a los humanos. Y se que te estás preguntado esto. Si, también se besan, algunas veces muy apasionadamente. (Aplausos) Algunos han aprendido a engañar a sus cónyuges. (Risas) Por ejemplo, la jacana africana: las hembras se aparean con diferentes machos y luego se va para buscar otros machos para aparearse, y deja al macho para cuidar de sus polluelos. (Risas) (Aplausos) Y las aves nos ayudan mucho, y a diario juegan papeles muy importantes en nuestros ecosistemas. Los buitres limpian nuestro medioambiente al digerir patógenos que causan enfermedades, y se terminan los cadaveres que tanto dinero nos costara limpiar del medioambiente. Una considerable bandada de buitres es capaz de dejar un cadáver del tamaño de una cebra completamente limpio. en tan solo 30 minutos. Los búhos ayudan a eliminar los roedores del medioambiente y esto es de gran ayuda porque nos ahorra dinero -- no perdemos nuestros cultivos -- y en segundo lugar, no tenemos que comprar productos nocivos para lidiar con estos roedores. Las hermosas suimangas que vemos en nuestro medioambiente son parte del equipo de polinización de la naturaleza, y ayudan a que nuestras plantas den frutos. Junto con otros polinizadores como insectos, nos han ayudado a obtener los alimentos de los que hemos dependido durante muchos años. Desafortunadamente, la historia de las aves no es perfecta. Se enfrentan a numerosos desafíos todos los días, donde sea que vivan. Las mayores amenazas que enfrentas las aves son la pérdida de su hábitat y la poca disponibilidad de comida. Las aves también son cazadas, especialmente las especies migratorias y patos que se juntan en en agua. Muchas aves que se mantienen juntas se están envenenando, especialmente en plantaciones de arroz. Ademas, las líneas eléctricas electrocutan las aves y los parques eólicos las despedazan cuando vuelan a través de las cuchillas. Hemos escuchado hablar sobre el cambio climático que ha generado muchos titulares y también está afectando a las aves, porque se ven forzadas a emigrar de sus lugares de cría a campos de alimentación porque desafortunadamente los lugares donde solían vivir ya no son habitables. Mi propia perspectiva hacia las aves cambió de pequeño cuando estaba en bachillerato, y vi que un chico golpeó y lastimó el ala y la pata de una ave llamada busardo augur. Yo estaba para allí, un chico de 14 años, e imaginé un ser humano en una situación similar, porque esta ave no pudo ayudarse a ella misma. Así que yo, que todavía no era un biólogo en aquel entonces, junté a tres de mis amigos y decidimos alojar al pájaro hasta que recuperara su fuerza para ser libre. Curiosamente, aceptó comer carne de la cocina de nuestra escuela, y cazamos termitas alrededor del recinto para su cena todos los días. En pocos días, había recuperado su fuerza y la liberamos. Estábamos tan felices de verla batir sus alas y volar graciosamente. Y esa experiencia cambió la forma en que miramos pájaros. De hecho, creamos una revista, y la llamamos la Revista Halcón, en honor del pájaro
that we had helped within our own high school. Those experiences in high school made me the conservationist I am today. And a passion for birds should especially matter for Africa and all Africans, because among all other continents, Africa hosts some of the most amazing bird species you can find anywhere in the world. Imagine having a name like "shoebill." That's the name of that bird. And there are countries like DR Congo, Tanzania, Uganda and Kenya who are leading the continent in highest numbers of diversity when it comes to the species. These birds continue to provide the continent with very crucial ecosystem services that Africa needs. Moreover, there is huge potential for Africa to lead the world in avian tourism. The economy will definitely benefit. Imagine how many communities will benefit from groups of tourists visiting their villages just to see the endemic birds that can only be found in those villages. How can we help birds together? There is now a chance for all of you to turn your passion for birds into contributing to their continued survival, and you can do that by becoming a citizen scientist. Citizen science is a growing trend around the world, and we are having scenarios where people are sharing information with the rest of the community about traffic updates, security alerts and so on. That is exactly what we realized as bird-watchers, and we thought, because birds are found everywhere, if we've got all of you and everyone else in Africa to tell us the birds they find where they live, where they school, or even where they work, then we can be able to come up with a map of every single species, and from there scientists will be able to actually prioritize conservation efforts to those habitats that matter the most. Take for example these two projects, the Africa Raptor DataBank, which is mapping all birds of prey in the continent of Africa, and the Kenya Bird Map, which is mapping about 1,100 species that occur in my country, Kenya. These two projects now have online databases that are allowing people to submit data, and this is converted into very interactive websites that the public can consume and make decisions from. But when we started, there was a big challenge. We received many complaints from bird-watchers, and they will say, "I'm in a village, and I cannot access a computer. How do I tell you what birds live in my home, or where I school, or where I work?" So we were forced to renovate our strategy and come up with a sustainable solution. It was easy: we immediately realized that mobile phones were becoming increasingly common in Africa and most of the regions could get access to one. So we came up with mobile phone applications that you can use on your iPhone and on your Android phone, and we made them freely available for every bird-watching enthusiast out there. So we came up with BirdLasser, which is used by the Kenya Bird Map, and also we have the African Raptor Observations, which is now used by the African Raptor DataBank. This was a huge breakthrough in our work and it made us get enormous amounts of data from every birder out there in the regions. With this, we realized that citizen science is indeed very powerful, the reason being, citizen science is adaptive. And we were able to actually convert many bird-watchers to start sharing new information with us. When we were starting, we didn't know that birds could be a huge gateway to approaching conservation of other forms of animals. Interestingly, now in the Virtual Museum for Africa, we have maps for dragonflies and damselflies, butterflies and moths, reptiles, frogs, orchids, spiders,
que habíamos ayudado dentro de nuestra escuela. Esas experiencias en la escuela me hicieron el conservacionista que soy. Y esta pasión por las aves debería ser importante para África y todos los africanos, porque de entre todos los continentes, África alberga algunas de las especies más increíbles que pueden encontrar en el mundo. Imaginen llamarse "factura de zapato". Ese es el nombre de esta ave. Y países como RD Congo, Tanzania, Uganda y Kenia lideran el continente con el mayor número de diversidad en cuanto a las especies. Estas aves le dan al continente el ecosistema que África tanto necesita. Además, es muy probable que África encabece el mundo del turismo aviar. La economía seguro se beneficiará. Imaginen cuántas comunidades se beneficiarán de los grupos de turistas visitando sus aldeas solo para ver las aves endémicas que solo se encuentran en esos pueblos. ¿Cómo podemos ayudar a las aves? Ahora todos Uds. pueden convertir su pasión por las aves en una aportación a su supervivencia continua, y pueden hacerlo si se interesan en la ciencia ciudadana. La ciencia ciudadana es una tendencia creciente alrededor del mundo, y tenemos escenarios donde las personas comparten información con el resto de la comunidad sobre actualizaciones de tráfico, alertas de seguridad, etc. Eso es exactamente lo que aprendimos como observadores de aves, y pensamos, porque los pájaros se encuentran en todas partes, Si Uds. y todos en África nos cuentan de las aves que ven de dónde viven, dónde estudian o incluso dónde trabajan, nosotros podríamos crear un mapa de cada especie, y de allí los científicos podrán priorizar los esfuerzos de conservación en los hábitats que más importan. Tomemos por ejemplo estos dos proyectos: El banco de datos Africa Raptor (ARDB, por sus siglas en inglés) que mapea todas las aves de rapiña en el continente de África, y el Kenya Bird Map, que mapea casi 1100 especies que viven en mi país, Kenia. Estos dos proyectos ahora tienen bases de datos en línea y permiten a las personas enviar datos, y esto se convierte en sitios web muy interactivos que podemos usar para tomar decisiones. Pero cuando comenzamos, hubo un gran desafío. Recibimos muchas quejas de observadores de aves, y decían: "Vivo en un pueblo, y no tengo una computadora. ¿Cómo les digo qué pájaros viven en mi casa o dónde estudio o trabajo?". Nos vimos obligados a renovar nuestra estrategia y crear un solución sostenible Fue fácil. Nos dimos cuenta de que los teléfonos móbiles eran cada vez más comunes en África y la mayoría de regiones tenían acceso a uno. Así que creamos aplicaciones móviles que pueden usar en su iPhone o Android, y las hicimos disponibles para todos los entusiastas que observan aves. Creamos BirdLasser que es usado por el Kenya Bird Map, y también tenemos el African Raptor Observations, que es usado por el Banco de datos African Raptor Este fue un gran avance en nuestro trabajo y nos hizo obtener enormes cantidades de datos de cada observador de aves en las regiones. Nos dimos cuenta de que la ciencia ciudadana es realmente muy poderosa, ya que la ciencia ciudadana es adaptable. Y pudimos hacer que muchos observadores de aves comenzaran a compartir información con nosotros. Cuando comenzamos, no sabíamos que las aves podrían ser el camino a la conservación de otras formas de animales. Interesantemente, ahora en el Museo Virtual para África, tenemos mapas para libélulas y caballitos del diablo, mariposas y polillas, reptiles, ranas, orquídeas, arañas,
scorpions, and yes, we are even mapping mushrooms. Who could have imagined mapping mushrooms? So this showed us that indeed we've created a community of people who care about nature in Africa. I hereby call upon all of you to join me in promoting the value of birds within your communities.
escorpiones, y sí, incluso estamos mapeando setas. ¿Quién podría imaginar mapear setas? Esto nos mostró que en realidad creamos una comunidad de personas que se preocupa por la naturaleza en África. Por este medio los animo a unirse y promover el valor de las aves dentro de sus comunidades.
Please just tell your friends about birds, for we are always inclined to love and care for that which we know. Please spend a few minutes in your free time
Por favor, solo cuéntenle a sus amigos de las aves, porque estamos inclinados amar y cuidar lo que conocemos. Por favor, dediquen unos minutos de su tiempo
when you are at work, at school, or maybe at home, to at least look around you and see which beautiful birds are there. Come join us in citizen science and tell us the birds you're finding in the places where you visit. Even simpler, you could buy your child or your sibling a pair of binoculars or a bird book
cuando estén en el trabajo, en la escuela o quizás en casa, a, al menos, ver a su alrededor y ver las hermosas aves que hay. Vengan y únanse a la ciencia ciudadana y cuéntenos de las aves que encuentran en los lugares que visitan. Más simple aún, podrían comprarle a su hijo o su hermano un par de binoculares o un libro de aves
and let them just appreciate how beautiful these birds are. Because maybe one day they will want to care for that one which they know and love. The children indeed are our future. Let us please teach them to love our feathermakers, because the love of birds can be a huge gateway to appreciating all forms of nature. Thank you very much. (Applause) Thank you.
y dejarlos apreciar lo bello que son las aves. Porque quizás un día ellos querrán cuidar lo que conocen y aman. Los niños de hecho son nuestro futuro. Enseñémosles a amar a nuestros fabricantes de plumas, porque el amor a la aves puede ayudarnos a apreciar todas las formas de la naturaleza. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos) Gracias.